A Guide to the 8th Evacuation Hospital 1941-2011
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
8th Evacuation Hospital, 1941-2011
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-5
18.25 linear ft. (38 boxes, ca. 18,000 items); correspondence, reports, photographs, 5 boxes of Byrd Stuart Leavell's manuscript, scrapbooks, and other archival material.
Of unique relevance to the University of Virginia Health System is the 8th Evacuation Hospital Collection. The 8th Evac. was organized and staffed by University of Virginia physicians and nurses during World War II. The collection contains scrapbooks, memoirs, reports, and numerous photographs that recall the experiences of the men and women who provided medical and nursing care in North Africa and Italy during the war.
Collected by Dr. John L. Guerrant, Thelma Matthews, Frank Lowther, William H. Laird, Ella Gillespie, Ruth Beery, Cathleene Carter, Helen Berkeley, Byrd Leavell, Prentice Kinser, Jr., Frances Wells Broadfoot, and other members of the 8th Evacuation Hospital unit
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The 8th Evacuation Hospital was organized and staffed by University of Virginia physicians and nurses during World War II. In February of 1942, University President John L. Newcomb and Dean of the School of Medicine, Harvey E. Jordan, gave permission for the organization of a medical unit for war service designed to be an evacuation hospital for emergency surgical cases. In March of 1942, Dr. Staige D. Blackford was made director of the unit. Dr. E. Cato Drash assisted Dr. Blackford in organizing a staff of over four hundred people for the 750-bed evacuation hospital, including 47 commissioned officers and 52 commissioned nurses. Ruth Beery, a former instructor at the School of Nursing, was made the principal chief nurse. Organization was completed by May of 1942.
The unit went through basic training during the summer of 1942 and was activated on August 19, 1942 under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Lincoln F. Putnam. In November of 1942, the men of the 8th Evacuation Hospital shipped out on the U.S.S. Santa Paula and went ashore at Casablanca where they set up a provisional general hospital at the former Italian consulate. Colonel John W. McKoan took over as commanding officer and oversaw the closing of the hospital four months after its establishment. During that time there were nearly 4,200 admissions and thousands of outpatients were treated in outpatient departments and the dental clinic.
On March 14, 1943 the 8th Evacuation Hospital moved to a new location on Anfa Hill where they were joined by 51 nurses and began to function as a convalescent hospital, caring for nearly 1,460 inpatients before being dismantled and parked in early June. The unit moved to a bivouac area at Camp Matifou, Algiers for six weeks until they were assigned to Salerno, Italy. After their arrival in Italy, they learned that all the hospital equipment had been lost, but they quickly managed to procure tents, a telephone system, generator and laboratory equipment. The hospital moved to Caserta and stayed there from October until December of 1943, and then spent three months in Teano functioning as a field hospital for combat operation. In Italy the hospital became very efficient at following the moving front line of the Allied forces. The Allied advance slowed in the fall of 1944 and the 8th Evac. was assigned to a muddy field in Pietramala, a mountainous area north of Florence, where they stayed for six months. The fall was wet and muddy and the winter cold and snowy. During this time the unit treated over 9,000 inpatients, of whom half were injured and wounded.
The end of fighting in Italy in the spring of 1945 meant that some members of the 8th Evac. were sent home, others to the Pacific, and others set up hospitals near Verona and Lake Garda. E. Cato Drash was made commanding officer as the 8th Evac. spent four months at Lake Garda treating almost 5,000 inpatients, mostly for disease. In the fall of 1945 the 8th Evacuation Hospital was demobilized after three and a half years of active duty. Over 48,000 patients, twice as many as were admitted to the University of Virginia Hospital in 1942-1944, were admitted to the 8th Evacuation Hospital in Africa and Italy over the three year period. Of those patients fourteen percent were injured, twenty-two percent were wounded, and sixty-four percent were sick. There were 253 deaths, or about half of one percent. More than 53,000 outpatients were seen in clinics.
The Hospital functioned in the heat of North Africa and southern Italy and in the rain, snow, and cold of the Italian mountains. At times the operating areas were all in use with a hundred men waiting for surgery, and at other times the staff had time on their hands and little to entertain themselves with. The unit received more awards, commendations, and decorations than most similar units and served longer in North Africa and Italy than any other American hospital. The men and women of the 8th Evacuation Hospital served their country well and were excellent representatives of the University of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The 8th Evacuation Hospital collection includes photographs, personal and official correspondence, reports, notebooks, purchase orders, citations, certificates, scrapbooks, newsclippings, insignia, and a manuscript of Byrd Stuart Leavell's book: The 8th Evac.: a History of the University of Virginia Hospital Unit in World War II (1970). Additional artifacts, including uniforms, plaques, and a replica set of Roman instruments, are in the artifact collection at the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Historical Collections, University of Virginia. Digital images of more than 75 photos related to the 8th Evacuation Hospital may be viewed at the University of Virginia Visual History Collection at http://mcgregor.lib.virginia.edu/prints/.
Contents List
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 1, ORGANIZATION OF THE UNIT 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-002)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 2, ACTIVE DUTY IN THE UNITED STATES 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-003)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 3, CONVOY TO AFRICA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-004)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 4, CASABLANCA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-005)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 5, SICILY AND ALGIERS 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-006)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 6, THE INVASION OF ITALY, ORAN, SALERNO, PAESTUM, AND CASERTA 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-007)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 7, CARE OF THE WOUNDED IN THE FIFTH ARMY AND OPERATION OF THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL IN ITALY 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-008)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 8, WINTER STALEMATE SOUTH OF ROME, TEANO (NEAR CASSINO) 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-009)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 9, SPRING OFFENSIVE; FROM THE GARIGLIANO TO THE ARNO (CARINOLA, CELLOLE, LE FERRIERE, GROSSETO, CECINA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-010)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 10, NORTHERN APENNINES, GALLUZZO (FLORENCE) 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-011)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 11, NORTHERN APENNINES, SECOND WINTER STALEMATE, PIETRAMALA 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-012)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 12, SUMMER OF FINAL VICTORY, THE PO VALLEY, LAKE GARDA, LEGHORN, THE SUMMING UP 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-013)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. APPENDIX 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-014)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. ENDNOTES AND BIBLIOGRAPHY 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 1 (Box-folder 01-015)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 1, ORGANIZATION OF THE UNIT 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-016)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 2, ACTIVE DUTY IN THE UNITED STATES 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-017)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 3, CONVOY TO AFRICA 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-018)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 4, CASABLANCA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-019)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 5, SICILY AND ALGIERS 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-020)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 6, THE INVASION OF ITALY, ORAN, SALERNO BAY, PAESTUM, AND CASERTA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph correction, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-021)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 7, CARE OF THE WOUNDED IN THE FIFTH ARMY AND OPERATION OF THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL IN ITALY 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-022)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 8, WINTER STALEMATE SOUTH OF ROME, TEANO (NEAR CASSINO) 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-023)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 9, SPRING OFFENSIVE; FROM THE GARIGLIANO TO THE ARNO (CARINOLA, CELLOLE, LE FERRIERE, GROSSETO, CECINA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-024)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 10, NORTHERN APENNINES, GALLUZZO (FLORENCE) 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-025)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 11, NORTHERN APENNINES, SECOND WINTER STALEMATE, PIETRAMALA 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-026)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 12, SUMMER OF FINAL VICTORY, THE PO VALLEY, LAKE GARDA, LEGHORN, THE SUMMING UP 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 2 (Box-folder 01-027)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. FORWARD, PREFACE AND TABLE OF CONTENTS, CHAPTER 1 ORGANIZATION OF THE UNIT 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-001)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 2, ACTIVE DUTY IN THE UNITED STATES 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-002)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 3, CONVOY TO AFRICA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-003)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 4, CASABLANCA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-004)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 5, SICILY AND ALGIERS 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-005)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 6, THE INVASION OF ITALY, ORAN, SALERNO, PAESTUM, AND CASERTA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-006)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 7, CARE OF THE WOUNDED IN THE FIFTH ARMY AND OPERATION OF THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL IN ITALY 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-007)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 8, WINTER STALEMATE SOUTH OF ROME, TEANO (NEAR CASSINO) 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-008)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 9, SPRING OFFENSIVE; FROM THE GARIGLIANO TO THE ARNO (CARINOLA, CELLOLE, LE FERRIERE, GROSSETO, CECINA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-009)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 10, NORTHERN APENNINES, GALLUZZO (FLORENCE) 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-010)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 11, NORTHERN APENNINES, SECOND WINTER STALEMATE, PIETRAMALA 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-011)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. CHAPTER 12, SUMMER OF FINAL VICTORY, THE PO VALLEY, LAKE GARDA, LEGHORN, THE SUMMING UP 1969, XEROX TMs with autograph corrections, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-012)
- MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE: THE 8TH EVACUATION HOSPITAL IN WORLD WAR II BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL. APPENDIX 1969, XEROX TMs, copy 3 (Box-folder 02-013)
- UNIVERSITY UNIT CALENDAR, CHRONOLOGICAL LIST OF PLACES IN WHICH 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL SERVED, FROM JAN. 1942 TO SEPT. 1945. 1970, carbon copy TMs, 1 PG. (Box-folder 02-014)
- ROSTER OF MEMBERS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL FOR THE APPENDIX OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE 1970, TMs with autograph corrections, 18 pp. (Box-folder 02-015)
- LEGENDS FOR PHOTOGRAPHS, LISTS OF PHOTOS AND THEIR I.D. NUMBERS, HAND DRAWN MAPS OF ITALY N. D., TMs with autograph corrections, A. MAPS AMs, 32 pp. (Box-folder 02-016)
- PUBLISHER'S PROOFS OF PHOTO ILLUSTRATION SECTION OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE 1970 JULY, 24 pp. (Box-folder 02-017)
- BILLS AND INVOICES INCIDENTAL TO THE WRITING AND PUBLICATION OF MUD, MOUNTAINS AND MEDICINE BY BYRD STUART LEAVELL AND SUMMARY OF COSTS SENT TO E. C. DRASH 1968-1970, Bills and invoices (Box-folder 02-018)
  THE DIETZ PRESS
- REVIEW OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE FROM RICHMOND TIMES DISPATCH BY JOHN A. OWEN 1970, TMs-6 pp. and ANS - 1 p. (Box-folder 02-019)
- REVIEW OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE BY H. ST. GEORGE TUCKER 1970, XEROX TMs 4 pp. (Box-folder 02-020)
- ADVERTISEMENTS FOR, AND REVIEWS OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE BY H. ST. GEORGE TUCKER AND MARY STEVENS JONES 1970, Newspaper clippings, 10 items (Box-folder 02-021)
- REVIEW OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE FROM RICHMOND TIMES DISPATCH BY H. ST. GEORGE TUCKER 1970 October 25, Newspaper clippings, 6 items (Box-folder 02-022)
- REVIEW OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE FROM RICHMOND TIMES DISPATCH BY H. ST. GEORGE TUCKER 1970 October 25, Xeroxed Newspaper clipping, 19 copies (Box-folder 02-023)
- MISCELLANEOUS NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS, INCLUDING NEWSPAPER ADS FOR MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE CA. 1943-1971, Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 02-024)
  J. PAUL WINTHROP OBITUARY, ELIZABETH ENGLEMAN, CATO DRASH
- NEWSPAPER AND OTHER CLIPPINGS OF REVIEWS OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE 1970, Clippings, Xeroxed copies of articles re 8th evac. (Box-folder 02-025)
- LETTERS FROM [LEON?] AND MME. G. GROSGEORGE TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1947 June 27 and June 23, ALS 3pp. (Box-folder 03-001)
- LETTER FROM [] TO MACON RE: SPECULATION ON POST-WAR U.S. ECONOMY 1946 October 26, ALS 1p. (Box-folder 03-002)
- LETTER FROM R.C. BARRETT TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD; LISTS OF PHOTOS WITH IDENTIFICATION NUMBERS; PLUS FLYER FROM U. S. ARMY RE AVAILABILITY AND USE OF PHOTOS 1949 March 16, TLS 1 pg., lists with autograph corrections 3 pp. (Box-folder 03-003)
- LETTER FROM RICHARD P. BELL TO BYRD S. LEAVELL RE: BELL'S RECOLLECTIONS OF ORTHOPEDIC SERVICE IN THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL 1968 March 21, TLS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-004)
- LETTER FROM EDMUND BERKELEY, JR. TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL 1968 August 5, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-005)
- LETTER FROM EDMUND BERKELEY, JR. TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL 1970 September 22, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-006)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO EVERETT P. AARON 1946 February 21, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-007)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO W. EDWIN HEMPHILL RE: RECORDS OF 8TH EVAC. UNIT AND POSSIBLE HISTORY 1946 March 16, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-008)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO CHESTER KEEFER RE: RECOMMENDATION FOR H. M. SMITH 1945 October 15, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-009)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO FRANK PLAISTED 1946 December 28, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-010)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO HERBERT M. SMITH RE: LETTERS OF RECOMMENDATION FOR SMITH 1945 October 11, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-011)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO PVT. JOHN D. SQUIER RE: SQUIER'S REQUEST FOR A PURPLE HEART 1945 November 13, Carbon copy TL 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-012)
- LETTER FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO FORMER MEMBERS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL RE: DIRECTORY, POSSIBLE HISTORY OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL 1945 November 1, mimeograph TL 1 pg.. (Box-folder 03-013)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF STAIGE D. BLACKFORD RE: 8TH EVAC. HOMECOMING PARTY 1945 November, carbon copy TL, ALS 4 pp. (Box-folder 03-014)
- LETTERS FROM FORMER MEMBERS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD RE: ACKNOWLEDGEMENT OF RECEIPT OF 5TH ARMY CITATION AND 8TH EVAC. DIRECTORY 1945 November 5-21, TLS, ALS 37 pp. (Box-folder 03-015)
- LETTERS FROM FORMER MEMBERS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD RE: ACKNOWLEDGEMENT OF RECEIPT OF 5TH ARMY CITATION AND 8TH EVAC. DIRECTORY 1945 Nov. 22-1946 Aug. 29, TLS, ALS 69 pp. (Box-folder 03-016)
- LETTERS FROM STAIGE D. BLACKFORD TO FORMER MEMBERS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL RE: DONATIONS TO 8TH EVAC. UNIT FUND AND POSSIBILITY OF WRITING HISTORY OF THE UNIT 1945 November- 1946 March, Carbon copy TL 18 pp. (Box-folder 03-017)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1945 October-1946 January, TL, ALS 13 pp. (Box-folder 03-018)
- LETTER FROM SALLY ANN BOARD TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: DONATION TO AM. ASSN. UNIVERSITY WOMEN FELLOWSHIP FUND 1971 May 17, ALS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-019)
- LETTER FROM SALLY E. BRIGHTMAN TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1945 December, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-020)
- LETTERS FROM MARGUERITE C. CASTON TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: ANSWER TO LEAVELL'S REQUEST FOR INFORMATION ON THE HISTORY OF THE GRACE LINE 1963 Jan. 31 and Feb. 11, TLS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-021)
- LETTER FROM GEN. MARK W. CLARK TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL REUNION 1950 July 7, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-022)
- LETTER FROM GEN. MARK W. CLARK TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL 1968 August, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-023)
- LETTER FROM JOHN W. DEMPSEY TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: DEMPSEY'S RECOLLECTIONS ON THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL 1968 June, AL 3pp. (Box-folder 03-024)
- LETTER FROM E. CATO DRASH TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: DRASH'S RECOLLECTIONS OF THE 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL IN CASABLANCA 1963 March 14, TLS 2pp. (Box-folder 03-025)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF E. CATO DRASH RE: RESPONSES TO INVITATIONS TO 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL REUNION 1970 July, ALS and Postcards 8pp. (Box-folder 03-026)
- LETTER FROM GILBERT R. HAILE TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: ANSWER TO LEAVELL'S REQUEST FOR INFORMATION FROM THE CHARLOTTESVILLE DAILY PROGRESS 1968 March 21, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-027)
- LETTER FROM FRANCES S. HUGHES TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: AM. ASSN. UNIVERSITY WOMEN 1971 May 24, ALS 3 pp. (Box-folder 03-028)
- LETTER FROM EPPA HUNTON TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL 1968 February 14, TLS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-029)
- LETTER FROM CAPT. RICHARD E. KATBOLI TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: MEDICAL SERVICE IN VIETNAM COMPARED TO 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL EXPERIENCE 1971 March 10, ALS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-030)
- LETTER FROM REV. RICHARD J. KIRK TO E. CATO DRASH RE: DRASH'S GIFT TO ST. PETER'S EPISCOPAL CHURCH IN MEMORY OF REV. WILLIAM LAIRD 1975 May 5, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-031)
- LETTER FROM LEWIS W. KIRKMAN TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1946 October 17, ALS 6 pp. (Box-folder 03-032)
- LETTER FROM LEWIS W. KIRKMAN TO 8TH EVAC. REUNION COMMITTEE 1975 June 29, ALS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-033)
- LETTER FROM CONSTANCE LAIRD TO E. CATO DRASH RE: DEATH OF W. LAIRD 1975 May, ALS 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-034)
- LETTER FROM WILLIAM LAIRD TO LEWIS W. KIRKMAN 1969 January 9, ALS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-035)
- LETTER FROM [AL?] TO BYRD STUART LEAVELL RE: RECOLLECTIONS OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL N.D. [1968?], AL 3 pp. (Box-folder 03-036)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO WILLIAM B. BEAN 1971 August 16, TLS 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-037)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO EDMUND BERKELEY 1969 April 14, 10, Carbon copy TMs 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-038)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO FRANCIS L. BERKELEY, JR. RE: PUBLICATION OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE 1969 September 23, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-039)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1969 August 12, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-040)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO STAIGE D. BLACKFORD 1970 September 9, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-041)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO DAVID T. BRYAN RE: POSSIBLE REVIEW OF MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE BY THE RICHMOND TIMES DISPATCH 1970 September 9, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-042)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO HENRY CARR RE: PUBLICATION OF 8TH EVAC. HISTORY AND REUNION 1970 September 9, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-043)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO BERNARD CHAMBERLAIN 1969 June 16, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-044)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO JOHN DEMPSEY 1961 January 11, Carbon copy TL 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-045)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO E. CATO DRASH 1971 March 2, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-046)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO GEORGE HARPER RE: THE POSSIBILITY OF HARPER REVIEWING MUD, MOUNTAINS, AND MEDICINE 1969 May-August, Carbon copy TL 4 pp. (Box-folder 03-047)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO BOYCE LOVING RE: LOVING'S REVIEW OF LEAVELL'S HISTORY OF 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL 1971 October 5, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-048)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO MRS. PETER MASON RE: REJECTION OF 8TH EVAC. HISTORY MS. BY UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA PRESS... 1969 May 16, Carbon copy TL 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-049)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO MRS. PETER MASON RE: GEORGE HARPER REVIEW 1969 August 12, Carbon copy TL with T.N. 2 pp. (Box-folder 03-050)
- LETTER FROM BYRD STUART LEAVELL TO BRIG. GEN. JOSEPH I. MARTIN RE: 8TH EVAC. HOSPITAL REUNION 1950 August 21, Carbon copy TL 1 pg. (Box-folder 03-051)